can it make it worse yes when it is
mismanaged and not properly explained to
a patient or misunderstood by a patient
or user error on the patient's end
should it make it worse
no PSA in and of itself is not
indicative of BPH PSA is extremely
transient if you understand the things
that drive PSA you wouldn't be as
concerned and as obsessed with it
especially when you take a snapshot in
time which is essentially what a blood
drill lab is uh
however BPH in and of itself is
something that will occur in every male
if we live long enough to experience it
a 90y old will always have a larger
prostate than a 19-year-old and there's
nothing anyone can do about that however
people always blame testosterone why
because around the age where Men start
to experience some levels of B pH and
around the age where men initially start
testing PSA which it according to the
American neurological Association is at
the age of 40 and up that is usually
also when men go on testosterone so the
correlation of the timeline for when
people start to look at something
coupled with when they start
testosterone happens to line up so
testosterone always takes the blame okay
if I brush dust under my rug for 10
years and I never look under the rug I
don't know that there's dust there it's
presumed but it is not evidence if I
happen to have my doorbell ring 10 years
from now and as the doorbell rings I
lift up my rug and I see all the dust
from all the years can I now safely say
that when the doorbell rings it causes
dust to
accumulate because they happen to be
around the same time the answer is no
unfortunately Men start testosterone
around the time when they start regular
Urology visits for their prostate and
that correlation is made there is no
evidence whatsoever and Morgan told out
of Harvard has done tons of research and
published a lot of literature on this I
attended a seminar earlier this year uh
specifically on prostate cancer and
testosterone therapy and it was three
days of him explaining and presenting
the evidence of why there isn't any um
so again it's been debunked but it
doesn't matter how many times we beat
this dead horse just like with estrad
people will continue to believe what
they want to believe they'll continue to
go after the old science of their pcps
their endos and the Euros
and they'll just keep saying estrogen's
bad for you and testosterone causes
prostate cancer and this is this is the
exhausting part of what we do
unfortunately